Finding Aid for Faculty and Staff Assistance Program (University of Michigan) records, 1973-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Faculty and Staff Assistance Program (University of Michigan) records 1973-1996, 1980/1993
University of Michigan. Faculty and Staff Assistance Program.
7 linear feet
93832 Bimu 2
University program designed to assist individuals having problems associated with alcohol, drug abuse, family or child related concerns, job dissatisfaction, and financial and legal difficulties. Also coordinated the Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs. Records document the development of an employee assistance program at the University of Michigan and its involvement in larger substance abuse issues across campus. Records include historical files, administrative files, collected reference materials, correspondence, Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs files, and Initiative on Alcohol and Other Drugs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor Nos. 8055 and 8050 ) was received beginning in 1992. 8055
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Faculty and Staff Assistance Program (FASAP) at the University of Michigan traces its origins back to 1973, when Staff and Union Relations (a sub-unit of Personnel, now Human Resources and Affirmative Action) appointed the Troubled Employee Research and Study Committee. Chaired by Carol Surles, the committee worked for a year studying the various behavioral-medical problems that interfere with job performance and drafted a proposal for a troubled employee program. In response to the recommendations of the committee, Staff and Union Relations assigned a half-time personnel representative in July 1975 to implement and coordinate an employee referral program. Despite the fact that this early attempt was informal and unpublicized, the response was great enough to indicate the need for an official, highly publicized program. As a result, FASAP was formed in 1977 and designated as the internal, university employee assistance program.
FASAP assists individuals who have or may potentially have problems associated with alcohol, drug abuse, family or child-related concerns, financial or legal difficulties, emotional concerns, medical behavioral problems, and job dissatisfaction or career concerns. Services are available to all university faculty, staff, retirees, family members, and/or their operating units and supervisory personnel. Program services include confidential consultation and diagnosis, referral, and follow-up. Additionally FASAP provides crisis intervention services, and training or consultation to administrators and supervisors in identifying and referring individuals whose personal problems are affecting work performance and unit morale. Individuals may go to FASAP at any time or be suggested to seek FASAP assistance by a friend, co-worker, or supervisor.
The Ann Arbor campus has a central campus office and a medical center office. The medical campus office opened in September 1986. FASAP counselors are available to assess and refer individuals to the variety of services both within the university community and to private agencies outside of it. Dearborn and Flint campuses have on-site offices. Designated persons within the counseling services departments have responsibility for providing the range of FASAP services at these locations.
The FASAP office was critical to the Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs which was appointed by President Duderstadt in 1989. Keith Bruhnsen, manager of FASAP, was called upon to coordinate the project. The task force was charged with developing a university-wide plan for dealing with the problems caused by alcohol and other drugs. In May 1991 it published its report, " A University Community Approach to Alcohol and Other Drugs Phase One Report of the University of Michigan Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs: The Rollicking Crew" Revisited," and in 1992 the University of Michigan Initiative on Alcohol and Other Drugs was established to implement its recommendations. Dr. Frederick Glaser, co-chair of the task force, was selected to head the Initiative, and Keith Bruhnsen was deeply involved in the new organization's work.
Originally, FASAP was administered by the Office of Staff Benefits. In 1990, it was moved to the Personnel Support and Development Office of Personnel Administration, now a part of the reconfigured Human Resources and Affirmative Action Office.
An overview of FASAP and its services is available at the following URL: http://www.umich.edu/~fasap/.
FASAP Coordinators
1977-1982 Mike Bologea
1982-1984 Edna Adelson
1984-1990 Keith Bruhnsen
FASAP Managers
1990-1998 Keith Bruhnsen
1998- Thomas R. Waldecker
The records of the Faculty and Staff Assistance Program (FASAP) document the approach taken by the university to assist employees troubled by medical, financial, family or work-related problems. The records span the years 1973-1996, with the bulk of the materials covering 1980-1993. Documentation details the evolution and development of FASAP and its involvement in larger substance abuse issues across campus. The records are divided into six series: Historical Files, Administrative Files, Collected Reference Materials, Correspondence, Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs, and Initiative on Alcohol and Other Drugs.
Subjects:
Alcoholism and employment--Michigan.; Drugs and employment--Michigan.; Employee assistance programs--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Faculty and Staff Assistance Program.; University of Michigan--Employees.; University of Michigan. Substance Abuse Center.; University of Michigan. Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs.; Substance abuse--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Prevention.; Alcoholism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Drug abuse--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Employees--Counseling of.
- Historical Files
  The Historical Files series contains documentation on the Troubled Employee Study Committee chaired by Carol Surles during 1973-1974. The recommendations of the study committee ultimately formed the basis of an employee assistance program which became FASAP. The folder "An Historical Overview of FASAP" is a compilation of the work of FASAP and its precursors from 1975 through 1981. The assembled documents include quarterly reports of activities, goals and objectives, and usage statistics. Other materials detail the development of FASAP through 1980.
  - "An Historical Overview of FASAP," (includes quarterly and other reports) 1975-1981 (Box 1)
  - Background 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Basic Program Data 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Supervisory Training Material (Carol Surles) 1977 (Box 1)
  - Troubled Employee Study Committee (Carol Surles) 1973-1974 (Box 1)
- Administrative Files
  Detailed information on the operation of FASAP is housed in the Administrative Files Series. A number of activity reports and monthly statistical data are located within this series along with policy documents and procedure manuals. A 1985 annual report and a 1993 report on the first 15 years of FASAP provide good overviews of the scope of FASAP's work and the evolving types of cases and issues addressed by the staff. The establishment of a FASAP office on the medical campus is well documented and is supported by minutes of the FASAP Medical Center Advisory Committee. Monthly analysis reports of caseload data are available from 1977 to 1990. Some statistical information is also present for the Dearborn campus for 1980 and 1983 as well as the medical campus office for 1986-1988. The data in these statistical analyses typically include the type of problem, client job category, and referring source.
  - Alcohol/Drug Report 1988 (Box 1)
  - Analysis Report 1981 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report 1985 (Box 1)
  - 15 Year Status Report 1993 (Box 1)
  - Blank Forms (Box 1)
  - Brochures (Box 1)
  - Data Intake Manual 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Dearborn Campus 1978, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Goals and Objectives 1980, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Medical Center (Expansion of FASAP to) 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Medical Center FASAP Advisory Committee
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - Planning and Review 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Presentation Information 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - Procedures Manual
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
  - Program Activity Reports
    - Performance Activity Reports 1977 (Box 1)
    - Case Load Data Analysis (monthly)
      - Ann Arbor Campus 1978-1990, 13 folders (Box 1)
      - Dearborn Campus 1980, 1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Medical Campus 1986-1988 (Box 2)
    - Monthly Activity Reports 1989-1992 (Box 2)
  - Reorganization 1989-1990, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Referral Guide 1988 (Box 2)
  - Staff and Work Team Meeting Minutes 1996 (Box 2)
  - Standard Practice Guide (FASAP Sections 201.14, 201.15) 1983-1987 (Box 2)
  - Trends in Case Activity 1991 (Box 2)
  - Utilization Data 1981-1984 (Box 2)
- Collected Reference Materials
  The Collected Reference Materials series consists of brochures, flyers, and pamphlets that FASAP collected from Michigan agencies and companies that in some way relate to the FASAP program. The materials, dating from 1978 to 1989, are arranged into three categories: Employee Assistance Programs, Treatment Facilities, and Miscellaneous items. The Miscellaneous folder includes reports on drug testing in the work place, drug policies of specific companies, and newsletters.
  - Employee Assistance Programs 1978-1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Treatment Facilities undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous undated
- Correspondence
  Correspondence dates from 1979 to 1994 and reflects the work of various FASAP coordinators and mangers. The correspondence also illuminates some of the policy issues developed and handled by FASAP. Both incoming and outgoing letters are found in this chronologically arranged series which includes correspondents from within the university as well as outside of the university setting.
  - 1979-1994, 14 folders (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files consist of files created and compiled by FASAP staff members and date from 1978 to 1996. Arranged alphabetically, the topical files include reports and minutes of various committees and task forces relating to alcohol, drug, and substance abuse issues (information on the Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs is located in a separate series). Notable topics include material on substance abuse among health care workers. This subject is profiled under several different folder headings, including "Chemical Dependency in Nurses," "House Officers and Medical Center Drug Testing," "Impaired Physicians," and "Medical Center Alcohol and Drug Testing." Training material illustrates efforts to teach supervisors how to identify and deal with employees in need of assistance. The file "Alcohol and Drugs in the Work Place Supervisory Handouts and Reference Materials" is a good example of training offered by FASAP.
  The topical files also document the reaction of the university to the problems of substance abuse among faculty and staff. Much of this documentation is found under the University of Michigan Substance Abuse Center (UMSAC). UMSAC was established in 1988 to coordinate substance abuse research and treatment activities. Several folders on UMSAC reflect the close association with FASAP as well as policy development, evaluation, and training to the university population.
  There is also documentation on non-university organizations dealing with substance abuse to which either FASAP itself, or individual staff members, belonged. Materials on the Association of Labor-Management Administrators and Consultant on Alcoholism (ALMACA), a Virginia based organization which promotes and assists in employee assistance programs, includes minutes and a position paper on alcohol and drug abuse in the work place. The Michigan Consortium on Substance Abuse Education (MCSAE) is an organization comprised of institutions of higher education. MCSAE documentation includes directories of substance abuse programs and faculty at Michigan colleges and universities. Finally, the "Washtenaw County Employer Substance Abuse Survey," contains information on how local businesses addressed the problem of substance abuse among their employees.
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Substance Abuse 1987 (Box 3)
  - Alcohol and Drugs in the Work Place
    - Supervisory Handouts and Reference Materials 1991 (Box 3)
    - Trainer's Manual 1990 (Box 3)
  - Alcohol Awareness Week 1986-1988 (Box 3)
  - Alcohol Task Force (Housing Division) 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - ALMACA (Association of Labor-Management Administrators & Consultants on Alcoholism, Inc.) 1981-1987 (Box 3)
  - Benefits and Case Management 1993 (Box 3)
  - Benefits Proposal 1993 (Box 3)
  - Blue Cross/Blue Shield 1983, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
  - Care Choices (HMO) Substance Abuse Coverage 1991 (Box 3)
  - Chemical Dependency in Nurses 1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - Cocaine 1986-1990 (Box 3)
  - Condition of Employment Letter 1978 (Box 3)
  - Condition of Employment Staff and Union Relations 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Co-payment Fund 1993 (Box 3)
  - Critical Incidents Task Force (Medical Center) 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Directory of Services 1983 (Box 3)
  - Discipline Guides 1983 (Box 3)
  - Dow Chemical Training Program 1988 (Box 3)
  - Drug Diversion and Impaired Nursing Study 1988 (Box 3)
  - Drug Free Workplace Act 1989 (Box 3)
  - Drug Testing 1984-1989 (Box 3)
  - Drug Testing in the Workplace 1987 (Box 3)
  - Drugs in the Workplace Substance Abuse Policies 1989 (Box 3)
  - Emergency Fund 1992-1996 (Box 3)
  - Employee Health Services Drug Testing Protocol 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Faculty/Staff Intervention 1990 (Box 3)
  - Gomberg, Edith (Professor of Psychology, includes outline for Social Work course "Drugs, Society and Human Behavior") 1989-1991 (Box 3)
  - Grad Care 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Holiday Campaign (Alcohol Awareness) 1987-1990 (Box 3)
  - Hospital Information Services-Stress Debriefing 1989 (Box 3)
  - House Officers Program 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - House Officers and Medical Center Drug Testing 1993 (Box 3)
  - Housing Division Task Force on Alcohol (See: Alcohol Task Force) (Box 3)
  - Huron Valley Nurses Peer Assistance Network 1986-1989 (Box 3)
  - Impaired Health Employees 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Impaired Physicians 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations 1989 undated (Box 3)
  - Intra-State Conference 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Leaders in Prevention 1989 (Box 3)
  - Medical Center Alcohol and Drug Testing 1988-1993 (Box 3)
  - Medical Center Program for Supervisory Personnel Trainer's Manual 1990 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Chemical Dependency Study Group 1987 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Consortium on Substance Abuse Education (MCSAE)
    - General 1983-1993 (Box 4)
    - Directory of Substance Abuse Education at Michigan Colleges and Universities 1984 (Box 4)
    - Directory of Substance Abuse Faculty at Michigan Colleges and Universities 1986 (Box 4)
  - Nurse Counselor (at FASAP) 1991 (Box 4)
  - Occupational Health Program Advisory Committee 1994 (Box 4)
  - Paper: "Taking A Look at the Employee Assistance Program," 1985 (Box 4)
  - Physician's Statement (Release of Medical Information) 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Referral for Monitored Assistance (RMA) Procedures 1983 (Box 4)
  - Referral Letters (Samples) 1977-1986 (Box 4)
  - REHAB Minutes 1983 (Box 4)
  - Release of Information 1984 (Box 4)
  - Risk Reduction and Responsible Hospitality Training Overheads undated (Box 4)
  - Self-Assessment Alcohol Screening Instrument 1992 (Box 4)
  - Sexual Harassment 1980 (Box 4)
  - Sick Time Study 1987-1989 (Box 4)
  - Single Parent Support Group 1989 (Box 4)
  - Smoking Policy (Box 4)
  - Smoking Withdrawal Program 1980 (Box 4)
  - Social Issues Newsletter and Articles 1993 (Box 4)
  - Social Work Presentation 1984 (Box 4)
  - State of Michigan Drug Testing Legislation 1987 (Box 4)
  - Substance Abuse Education Network (SAEN) 1989-1993 (Box 4)
  - Substance Abuse in the Workplace: Awareness, Intervention and Prevention-A program for Supervisory Personnel Training Manual (Draft) 1988 (Box 4)
  - Substance Abuse Prevention Activities 1986-1988 (Box 4)
  - Substance Abuse Prevention Program 1987-1989 (Box 4)
  - Substance Abuse Training Program University Hospital 1983-1989 (Box 4)
  - Supervisor Training Film 1993 (Box 4)
  - Supervisor Training Overheads undated (Box 4)
  - Supervisory Referral Guide 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Supervisory Training Materials 1985-1988 (Box 4)
  - Survey of Knowledge, Attitudes and Beliefs about Pertinent Health Issues Among U of M Students Living in Residence Halls 1988 (Box 4)
  - Task Force on Mental Health and Substance Abuse (Dr. Greden) 1995 (Box 4)
  - Task Force on Sexual Orientation 1986-1989, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Third Party Billing 1981-1983 (re: insurance claims) (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan Substance Abuse Center (UMSAC)
    - Activity Summary 1993 (Box 4)
    - Evolution of the Center 1994 (Box 4)
    - Interdependencies between UMSAC and the Initiative 1994 (Box 4)
    - Members by Unit 1994 (Box 4)
    - Mission Statement Summary 1994 (Box 4)
    - Recommendations 1994 (Box 4)
    - Substance Abuse Task Force 1985-1986 (Box 4)
    - Substance Abuse Center 1988 (Box 4)
    - Substance Abuse Center Funding Proposal 1989 (Box 4)
    - Retreat 1990 (Box 4)
    - Retreat 1993 (Box 4)
    - Steering Committee Reports 1988-1990 (Box 5)
    - Steering Committee Minutes 1989-1994, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan Survey Regarding Alcohol and Other Drugs 1993
    - "All Respondents Stub and Banners," 1993 (Box 5)
      (statistical data from survey)
    - Background and Summary September 13, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Statistical Data 1993 (Box 5)
    - Staff Statistical Data 1993 (Box 5)
- Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs
  The Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs series provides evidence of FASAP manager Keith Bruhnsen's contributions as coordinator of the task force appointed by President James D. Duderstadt in 1989. The 60-member task force consisted of faculty, staff and students. These files document the start up and progress of the task force. The committees subseries reflects the workings of the four major committees (Coordinating, Identification and Intervention, Policy, and Prevention and Education) and include minutes, reports, and transcripts from public hearings. The task force's final report and recommendations are found within this series. The Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs led to the establishment of the Initiative on Alcohol and Other Drugs.
  - Washtenaw County Employer Substance Abuse Survey 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Administrative
    - General 1989-1991 (Box 5)
    - Budget 1989-1991 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1989-1992 (Box 5)
    - Final Report "A University Community Approach to Alcohol and Other Drugs" (Rollicking Crew Revisited) 1991 (Box 5)
    - Focus Groups 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Incidents 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Insurance Committee 1991 (Box 5)
    - Master File on Policies, Reports/Documents, and Supporting Data 1989 (Box 6)
    - Meeting Minutes 1989-1991 (Box 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1989-1993 (Box 6)
    - Prevention Conference 1990 (Box 6)
    - Reconvening-Follow Up Meeting (Includes annual report of Initiative on Alcohol and Other Drugs) 1993 (Box 6)
    - Security Reports 1991 (Box 6)
    - Survey of Policies and Programs 1990-1991 (Box 6)
    - U of M Comprehensive Alcohol-Free Recreation and Entertainment for Students (M-CARES) Grant Application 1992-1994 (Box 6)
  - Committees and Subcommittees
    - Co-Chairs/Coordinating Committee 1990-1991 (Box 6)
    - Identification and Intervention Committee
      - Faculty Subgroup 1990 (Box 6)
      - Literature Review 1990 (Box 6)
      - Meetings 1989-1990 (Box 6)
      - Public Hearing December 11, 1989 (Box 6)
      - Reports 1990-1991
      - Policy Committee
      - General 1989-1991 (Box 6)
      - Meetings 1989-1990 (Box 6)
      - Public Hearing November 27, 1989 (Box 6)
      - Report 1990 (Box 6)
    - Prevention/Education Committee
      - Literature Review 1990 (Box 6)
      - Minutes 1989-1990 (Box 6)
      - Public Hearing December 4, 1989 (Box 6)
      - Reports 1991 (Box 6)
    - Staff/Data Group Minutes 1989-1990 (Box 6)
- Initiative on Alcohol and Other Drugs
  The Initiative on Alcohol and Other Drugs series is divided into four subseries. The first subseries, Administration, contains the records of the Initiative's staff meetings, as well as meetings of two bodies established to oversee the Initiative's efforts: the Policy Council and the Program Council. This series also contains records from the Initiative Transition Team, an internal group which met to analyze progress in reaching the goals set for it by the recommendation of the Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs. The second subseries, Phase I Activities, documents efforts to conduct a university-wide survey on attitudes towards drugs and alcohol, establish policies for dealing with alcohol and other drugs, and explore ways to monitor the effects of alcohol and other drugs on the university community. The third subseries, Phase II Activities, contains records of the Initiative's efforts to "address the more fundamental and longer range issue of the implications of the use of alcohol and other drugs in society" (memo, 9-5-1990, Folder: Initiative Transition Team.) This subseries is arranged alphabetically, and consists largely of records documenting contacts with various groups within the university to collect relevant information about the affect of alcohol and other drugs on their activities. The fourth subseries, Topical Files, is arranged alphabetically and consists of materials relating to subjects such as the problems of alcohol and other drugs in society at large, the efforts of other universities to address similar issues, support and treatment groups for alcoholics, as well as background files on issues relating to the law and insurance.
  - Administration
    - Staff Meeting Agendas and Minutes 1992-1994 (Box 6)
    - Policy Council Agendas and Minutes 1991-1994 (two folders) (Box 6)
    - Program Council Agendas and Minutes 1994 (Box 6)
    - Initiative Transition Team Agendas and Minutes 1993-1994 (Box 6)
    - Retreat-Follow Up 1993 (Box 6)
  - Phase I Activities
    - Telephone Survey of Other Institutions (Box 7)
    - University Survey (Box 7)
    - Unit Policy Review
      - General File (Box 7)
      - Internal Policies in List 1989-1990 (Box 7)
      - Business and Finance Division (Box 7)
      - College of Literature, Science and Arts (Box 7)
      - Interfraternity Council (IFC) (Box 7)
      - Law School (Box 7)
      - Medical Center (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous Units (Box 7)
      - Office of Academic Affairs (Box 7)
      - Office of Development (Box 7)
      - Office of Student Affairs (Box 7)
      - School of Dentistry (Box 7)
      - School of Education (Box 7)
      - School of Music (Box 7)
      - School of Nursing (Box 7)
      - University of Michigan, Dearborn (Box 7)
      - University of Michigan, Flint (Box 7)
    - Monitoring Data
      - Data Collection and Reports (Box 7)
      - Completed Critical Incident Reports (Box 7)
      - Units Not Selected for Data Collection (Box 7)
      - Alumni Association (Box 7)
      - Athletics (Box 7)
      - Housekeeping Units (Box 7)
      - Plant Operations (Box 7)
      - Risk Management (Box 7)
      - Final Copy of Notes for Committee (Box 7)
      - "Monitoring Data on Impact of Alcohol and Other Drugs at UM: Progress Report," 1993 (Box 7)
  - Phase II Activity
    - Ann Arbor Police Data (Box 7)
    - Blue Cross/Blue Shield, MCARE, Care Choices (Box 7)
    - Business Residence, Inglis House, Oxford (Box 7)
    - Counseling Services (Box 7)
    - Data Systems (Box 7)
    - Department of Public Safety (Box 7)